[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
i really wanted to let that go for a bit
but we have to
begin uh welcome to the store everyone
peter limber steward of the store
the place where we cohere and dialogue
but what matters most
the nice edge at this very moment and
today we have my fellow meta
tribalist tyler alterman here with us
today
and i think it was like uh a year ago
you just
like you emailed me and you're like hey
i'm coming to toronto let's meet i'm
like who's this guy
[Laughter]
okay let's meet and then we had a drink
and it was awesome uh really great
conversation
and then he texted me afterwards peter
you should be the mayor of toronto and
i'm like okay
bromance begins um so uh
tyler oh yeah your mute tyler i'll let
you on meet yourself if you want to rift
already
i was just going to say i meant it i
meant you should be the mayor i
i well i think i was specifically saying
you should be the mayor of the toronto
like scene and now i think you should be
the mayor of the
the entire scene my ego just
elevated that compliment that's my goal
um so yeah uh and tyler did this awesome
tweet thread
called uh the dawn of the meta tribe or
something like that
where he discusses this concept of the
meta tribe and how we're sort of in this
age where this thing could exist
um so we're going to jam rift on it a
little bit jam on it and
if you have any questions start throwing
the chats i'll call you and mute
yourself and imagine we'll have an
organic discussion
uh this will be on youtube so if you
don't want to be on youtube just
indicate that in chats
so any any opening thoughts um at the
risk of
monologuing any opening thoughts on uh
what the meta tribe is
yeah i told peter to stop me if i
started monologuing because i have
sometimes i have a bad habit um with
that
um which a few people here probably
already know but the first few minutes i
i was trying to i was shouting out a few
people in the audience but i think i was
muted the whole time
so hello friends um okay so
uh tldr i think the i would describe the
meta tribe
as being
something like more like a sociological
phenomenon than an actual social
movement
so i i would describe it as being
something distinct
uh type than something like game b
or meta modernism or effective altruism
or the or the rationality movement
because with each of these different
things
they they tended to have
some amount of some greater amount of
central organization
i mean to a certain degree the type
already existed
uh and the organizers coalesce those
people so you know
in the case of rationality movement you
had eleazar writing
not a lot of people know this actually
about the rationality movement one of
the biggest things getting people into
the rationality movement was elias
writing harry potter and the methods of
rationality
which was a harry potter fan fiction and
then that in turn
was one of the biggest things
responsible for the creation of the
effective altruism movement
um because the rationality movement fed
into that um but then the
the effect of altruism movement itself
also i think you had will
will mccaskill earlier on earlier today
um had a set of extremely competent
organizers right at the beginning i
think will was there at the beginning
um you had toby or there at the
beginning um you had jeff anders there
at the beginning and they they all sort
of like coalesced and formed a
conference
um to deliberately coin the term and
cohere the thing as a movement
um this is a lot of shocking for not
describing what the meta tribe is
basically i think that
the meta drive isn't like that in that
it's kind of more
a set of people who find themselves at
the end
of fixed points of view
um who find themselves at the end of not
only modernism
and and post-modernism but um find
themselves in a place
where it doesn't really make as much
sense to them to
say this is the one true ideology this
is the one true religion and so on
um however they've been typically there
are feeders
from these from these previous phenomena
so rationality seems like it's a big
feeder
i would say effective altruism as well
then you have events
um like burning man i would say is
another feeder and ephemeral just sort
of like burning man at sea for
silicon valley people um and then and
then there are things which are more
almost like pure metatribe which i
describe as feeders to the
to the broader meta tribe which i would
think game b is this
the stoa is this um daniel
schmuckenberger
feeds a lot of people into it and then
um but the highest concentration
interestingly i think is this sort of
weird conversational shelling point or
gathering place
that you find in a specific
algorithmically created
section of twitter like the way it's
been created
but you know people talk about twitter
being hell and and people constantly
like
verbally assaulting one another but
there's this one section of sort of meta
tribe twitter
that's evolved out of what you might
call and i can i can define some of
these terms but out of post-rationalist
twitter and
rationality twitter where everyone is
just really nice
and trying to earnestly like take pretty
uh non-partisan views on all sorts of
different issues
discuss things um with some semblance of
rationality but like not leaving out
romanticism um
and uh it's largely sort of the
algorithm to thank in in a particular
way because it's all the people
liking each other's uh comments and then
being suggested
uh a profile which is a which is more of
the same essentially
so it's one of these things that's kind
of emerged i would say most in twitter
as
due to these algorithmic bubbles but
then you see it taking place all over
physically in the world too so i would
say that there are pretty physical
metatribe networks too
but i want to emphasize that it's not
like a formally at least the way i see
it it's not a formally organized thing
but more an emergent phenomenon
of a bunch of people who have all read
similar books and engaged similar memes
and
and so forth i mean peter i'd be curious
to have you um
i'd be curious to have you define it
because the the way that i heard the
term was from you
um it was uh between a conversation
between you and daniel thorson
i think on i forget whether it was your
podcast or his
um and then and then it might have
originally come from jared
james but you guys i felt like fleshed
it out during that conversation
right i can't remember what daniel and i
were talking about but the conversation
that
is coming to mind is the one i had uh
with jason snyder that who's in the room
right now from the both
uh podcast and jason's like he's like
the super connector of the meta tribe i
don't even think he likes the word meta
but anymore but uh
and we were talking with jared uh jason
colin morris and
tim adeline um and i mentioned
or just i don't know who mentioned this
but i got uh this
dichotomy of the kinetic tribe you know
like becoming tribal around your
neighbors and you know
resilience localism all that type of
stuff and the meta tribe
like kind of the people that resonate
with your ideas
who are in that kind of meta-modern
post-rational space
because they're not really next door i
can't really just say hey ring their
doorbell
but i can throw a beacon on the internet
like an event or a podcast right and a
truck and find the others that way
and then have and then the idea with
places like the stoa or inter intellect
all these other kind of campfires that
are emerging is to get into
you know relationship like like let's
feel each other let's talk to each other
let's kind of like um
you know belong together and you can do
that better on a zoom call rather than
just like a you know
a tweet um so that's the idea that get
the sense of tribalness
online with people who are into these
meta ideas and post-rational
proclivities
yeah and you know the interesting thing
about that word meta tribe is
it's pretty funny for for a couple
reasons one is that if you were to
try where if i think if you were to try
to assign
the label metatribe to to most meta
tribe members they wouldn't be
interested in having a label applied to
them
which is an interesting feature of a
tribe just because typically when we
talk about tribes
it's about kind of like you know wearing
your baseball jersey
and also your like yankees number one
mit on your on your hand
and through the meta tribe it feels
almost like the opposite because it's
those
it feels like it's a bunch of these kids
who never knew what lunch table to sit
at
in middle school um and who maybe you
know the way i described it which a
bunch of people reacted to very
viscerally
is sort of these in-betweeners who have
a bunch of friends
who are the skaters and a bunch of
friends who are the punks and a bunch of
friends with the drama kids and maybe
some friends who are the jocks
and then in today's you know more uh
post-middle school scene like a bunch of
friends who are social justice a bunch
of friends who are
hyper conservative or even neo-reaction
a bunch of people who are
grey tribe or rationalists and
scientists but then they don't really
identify with any of these things
and they typically feel not ostracized
that's the wrong word because a lot of
them are actually
sort of widely accepted by these groups
but maybe um
in some significant sense alone because
it never makes sense for them to just
see the world through any one of these
lenses um it's sort of one of these
things where
you know there's this fable of the blind
men trying to
piece together the elephant um and they
they take this seriously that um each of
these things is only feeling one part of
the elephant
um so that's that's the first reason i
feel like the meta tribe is funny and
then the second reason
is that it's one of these tribes that in
a funny way kind of
disdains the idea of an out group you
know it might
while i've well it's been my experience
that the meta tribe folks are
in favor of uh things like curation
um it seems like you know curation of
your allies curation of you know who
might join a meeting etc like not not
the sort of radical conclusion
necessarily
um they seem to be pretty against the
idea that there are like good guys and
bad guys or people to be
excluded because of their nature or or
what have you
and so i'm sort of on two fronts
the name kind of fails but then it does
really feel like there should be
at least a placeholder label to uh
to to describe the thing and i don't
think there's a really i don't really
think there's a better one
yeah i'm wondering what you think are
some
common characteristics of people who
would be you know fairly classified in
this meta tribe
um and i recall anna gatt who does the
inter intellect she had like a great
article that had like all these things
i'm like yep that's me that's me that's
me
um and with the the meta tribe what
comes to mind i was talking to aaron
lewis about this too but when you came
on my podcast
um it's like the grape hill the idea of
getting grape killed
uh absolutely that's funny this is that
the venkatesh route term so there's like
um
i like that you know you you don't take
a blue pill you're born into the blue
pill in a way you're born
normally reality and then you take a red
pill and the red bill could be
like anything could be social justice it
could be like some reactionary thing and
then it just really hardens you it
fossilizes your
worldview us versus them and then you
find your tribe through that idea
but then you take the gray pill and it
kind of muddies the waters a little bit
and then you're uncertain of your
previous red pill
um and then you're just kind of like you
know so basically you bounced around
maybe you took a couple of red pills
until you got to the the great pill and
i think
people who are in this had that
experience and then now they they have
this comfortable
relationship or they have a good
relationship with being in unknowingness
they don't have that existential anxiety
they got over that that phase
so i think that's one thing um and the
other thing is like this
bespoke journey everyone has this
eclectic bookshelf and
things there right first they read
nietzsche and then they read dune and
then they were
thinking fast and slow and then a
different person it's like first they
read permaculture and then they saw
daniel schmuckenberger videos it's
yeah it's rewinding and then there's
that that kind of like intellectual lone
wolf
auto didact quality there and i think
associated with that is the existential
loneliness
like to kind of really want to find the
others and so i feel like with the store
there's all these like
eclectic weirdos uh you know like kind
of like
like finding each other yeah and that's
i think the
i think part of the reason i wanted to
articulate this as a social as a
potential sociological phenomenon
is just to reify it so there could be a
little bit more of a beacon for the
people to find each other
despite um most meta tribers not wanting
to adhere to any labels
it does feel pretty important to be
having things like the stoa
or um a sort of a description of this
phenomenon so that the people can can
link up with one another
because whenever whenever i encounter
someone who i would consider
a sort of member of this demographic
they typically have this sort of jaw job
reaction
of me and the other people having read
many of the same books like how is it
that you have read keith johnstone's
impro and also saw him on the store last
week and then also
like you're interested in cognitive
science and
you've read a bunch of old school like
sociological texts
and and and typically they found
themselves to be the only person who
cares about all these things
and meanwhile they're also watching like
um
you know uh charlie kaufman films and
they're quite an aspect or like a
romantic in that way
and and typically they're you know they
can only find
uh like meet the needs to satisfy these
different parts of them
by hanging out with their particular
artist friend and then maybe next night
they'll discuss genetics with their
scientist friends
and then they typically don't have an
outlet to to
sort of synthesize them all but i think
actually you know
i don't think it's a special group in a
way i think it's just what we're seeing
is just the edge
of an inevitable historical it does
it almost like maybe even the breaking
of the historical cycle in a way
um because it seems like up until
something like the 1960s
uh the the sentence
the the overall narrative you could you
could describe
for for most people in the world is
here's what's going on
like that that that as a sentence where
whether it's here's what's going on
you're
um you you attend your job from nine to
five
you create an atomic family in the
suburbs that's one version
another version is here's what's going
on you're born into like a church family
you're you're a mormon for life um no
disrespect to the mormons i think
they're
pretty incredible faith um and then i
think after that
you see the the 1960s and the sort of
post-modern turn
where it's more like it's sort of the
red pill as you described it's going
from the blue pill to the red pill of
like
here's what's really going on so you go
from here's what's going on to here's
what's really going on
and then people are trying to
subversively describe
uh what appears to be the true
underlying structures of reality or
society
um in almost a sort of rebellious way
and then like you said typically
people often have a bunch of red pills
and then often they're in reaction to
one another
so you know i've met people who who took
like the social justice red pill
and then they took the new reaction red
pill and then only after that
did they come to some sort of synthesis
between these things um which you might
describe as like the gray pill
um or sometimes even the reverse i've
got i think i've encountered the reverse
only once um but nonetheless it's
happened
um and so it feels like the latest
version is something like i have no idea
what's going on
which is which is not to say let's not
figure out what's going on or like let's
not
adopt provisional ideas of what might be
happening and act on those
i think the meta tribe is unique in that
it actually does take action it's just
not it's not this post-modernist
malaise where it's like who knows what
is reality anyway let me play xbox or
something like that
um typically they're pretty active
people and they're trying to do things
like
solve existential risk um like um
the the agi problem or uh
or synthetic biology pandemics um or
they're trying to solve something like
the meaning crisis
so they're not inactive um but they are
going about things from
uh sort of a multi-perspective view
which just feels like
the inevitable thing to happen once you
have a world a globalized world full of
tons of clashing narratives
like it's impossible i've got this from
this line basically from uh
sorry foreal who's the head teacher at
monastic academy
where the way he describes it is nobody
believes the stories anymore
like typically you would grow up inside
of a story and adhere to it your entire
life and not have it be challenged
and now you get a different story from
your high school teacher and then when
you get home
you get a different story from your mom
and then when you go out and hang out
with your friends it's a totally
different story about like what life is
and what the world is from them
and so i think that inevitably is just
going to lead to a breaking point
because the mind seeks coherence it
doesn't
it doesn't sit well with um cacophony
and chaos
and i see the meta tribe is basically
attempting to to tame the chaos by
trying to find some
some synthesis path where you can have
all these
shifting truths and not be like
whirling through a maelstrom all the
time
i'm so going to pivot the chats in the
moment of the q a another thing i want
to present to you
um i noticed like maybe a meta tribal
skill set that i see is like the
metagame
um and i currently hold that as like
there's an ecology of games
that are currently playing and the
ability to zoom out and have choice of
which one you want to play
and then you and i had a good moment uh
when keith johnstone uh
uh the guy who kind of invented improv
came to the store robin hansen was there
and he asked him and then i primarily
message you like
robin is cute right and then you said
they're playing different games
because robin with like you know system
two analytical propositional mode
and keith johnson's like zero [ __ ]
given he's like you know like just doing
his own thing
um and so this idea of like not even
code switching perspectives but
code switching different games right
yeah and do you have any thoughts on
that
um i think yeah it's exhausting actually
uh someone that maybe they're here i
forget their twitter handle
but someone commented on twitter that um
being in this
in the sociological space of like high
betweenness centrality
um of being between all these different
scenes and not a part of any of them
um and being forced to switch games all
the time is is
is exhausting and also kind of
heartbreaking actually which is why it
feels nice to
finally be attempting to come together
because i i don't know about you but
most
most of my friends i would not give the
give the arbitrary label meta tribe um
you know i have friends who are
super conservative and trump supporters
i have friends who are super social
justice and marching in the streets
every day
um i'm friends with tons of people who
uh
the average post-rationalist might
describe as a normie or something like
that
um and i love them all like really
deeply
but then i do have to kind of play a
different game with each of them in
order to relate
i have to have to do this sort of
translational game um and so
it's just this experience of like i
think a lot of people
in this in this place who are
multi-hyphenate in this way like
scientist artist
basketball player or um gamer
uh biologist or what have you they're
kind of they're
they're finding that in order to get the
thing that every human yearns for
connection
they have to become masters of the
metagame you might say
um or as you put it actually you had a
good term for it which is something like
memetic mediators
um which i liked as as people who are
you know if you if you imagine all these
memes
swirling around in the atmosphere like
kind of like controlling
giant swaths of the population uh what
they have to be able to do
is walk in between the different swaths
to to learn from them and gain their
ideas and connect with them
um while also not being consumed by them
and a lot of these things a lot of these
swats
you know people describe them sometimes
on twitter as egregors which is an old
term
meaning like um thought forms basically
it comes from the occult uh like
aleister crowley and all them
uh the idea of uh something
that is basically a meme with agency
um so something that's like an idea or a
set of ideas but that seems to actually
behave kind of like a human
um or at least something that isn't
inanimate
um and then the thing about these things
about aggregors is they actually also
try to capture you
so like not only are you trying to to
jump over these um
fences in order to just commune with
people um in in their in their
in their game but then also the games
are often somewhat aggressive and trying
to capture you as well
um and often a bit zero sum so that's at
least a big part of my experience
what about you do you find it you seem
to be more chill about it actually
i'm trying to learn a sort of zen
attitude about it from what i
from what i get from your vibe yeah it's
like maybe a stoic
thing going on oh yeah yeah um
and uh one that came up uh i'm not maybe
taking jason for this one if
he's willing but the memetic mediation
thing you said uh
this jason i were having a letter
exchange and then this this term uh the
psychodynamic is political
uh came up and how like you know how the
metamoderns they call uh
philosophical allergies like you get
triggered by certain kind of
words or terms but yeah right use that
as an opportunity for like shadow work
so the culture war is an opportunity for
for shadow works as a memetic meteor you
go in you you adopt these reality
tunnels you get triggered
you do the work required that allows you
to talk to them vibe with them and stuff
like that
yeah i love that jason you would want to
add anything to that if
i lived in your mind if i can put you on
the spot
i can edit this part out of you if you
want me i'm not sure if i have much to
add i think you said it pretty well
peter
um yeah i mean my emphasis was for a
while was on
how it's a contemplative practice right
because you have to like you were saying
tyler you have to interact
with all these world views all these
memes and they trigger you in different
ways
and in order to like keep your head
above water you know you have to be able
to process all this stuff emotionally
right yeah mindfulness and all of that
and so
um uh but at the same time
i i i don't and this is more of a more
recent
a more recent uh place that i'm coming
to is that i don't think it's good for
anybody to be a memetic mediator all the
time or to
to be in this space where they're just
jumping around tribes and playing the
games because you end up playing
yourself
right interesting and you know like
for me it's like there's like this
balance of you know being this memetic
mediator role
this meta tribe type of thing and then
kind of settling down
into um domesticity i guess
or you know like like that there still
might be some tribes that you resonate
with more
and sometimes it's just good to like you
know be there for a while and then come
back
that's all i would add yeah and
practically that's what i end up doing
um although i don't know about you but i
i find that i
if i if i practice domesticity with any
particular sub tribe i start getting
antsy
because you know i'll hang out for
instance like in the bay area i was
living in the bay area for six years and
most of my tribe were
rationalists and effective outros
because back then i was one of the
people
uh running the effective altruism
movement um i was running the american
office of the
center for effective altruism at oxford
which i think will founded
or was at least one of the original
members of will mccaskill who you
mentioned
um but uh you know that being my crowd
like i became
i got cabin fever for wanting to like
go do contact improv or hang out with
actual artists and not just people
making like led burning man art who
happen to also be
mostly programmers for most of the day
um and so how do you
curious jason how do you manage that
cabin fever part if you practice also
the domesticity
um i don't i don't know
i mean it helps that i'm kind of like
you know we're all kind of locked down
you know what i mean so i don't actually
like get out much
and so i can kind of like keep up with
like what all of the different
scenes are doing you know remotely but
good point
no i see what you're saying though i
mean i think i think for a while i was
like on overdrive
and i was just kind of like many
different like private chat groups
you know all over twitter and and it was
just i think i just burned myself
out and so i think i'm probably at the
place now where
give me like two months or a month and
then i'll start itching to like
you know to branch out again and
i guess push myself in a different
direction um
so i don't know maybe maybe you're just
like i don't know
maybe how old are you maybe you're
younger than me maybe i'm just kidding i
don't know
okay so yeah i'm i'm i'm a few years
older than you so maybe i'm just getting
old
or maybe i'm more antsy yeah there we go
there we go
peter actually before we turned it to
the audience i had two questions for you
that i was that i'm still really curious
about so there are these two phenomena
that i'm linked to but that i don't
really
i wouldn't say i'm a part of its
demographic per se even though i
think that they're both parts of the
meta tribe so there's metamodernism
um which i feel like in its attitude
kind of describes almost exactly what
i'm talking about
as the implicit shared philosophy
between metatron members but it seems to
be a kind of
like sociologically distinct contingent
just in terms of like
the people who hang out with one another
inside of it um that's one and then
and then there's game b uh which i i'm
friends with a bunch of the game b
people like i'm friends with jordan
jordan green hall who
um i think was one of the original
creators um if not the original creator
um and then i'm curious as someone who i
perceive to be more involved with these
scenes what is there
how would you describe their overlap
with what you and i would describe as
the
which feels like a sort of more um a
wider meta tribe
and uh yeah both in terms of ideology
and maybe social like sociologically how
do they
relate like who's friends with who um
do you have a take on that um maybe i
can riff off uh your thoughts
my senses um
so i don't know enough about
metamodernism i whenever i ask someone
what should i read on it they point me
to the same book which i
abashedly still haven't read the the
listening society
um and that that that seems to be the
core text so i would have to really read
that before
i understood the ideological question
but at least
on the sociological question my sense is
that
that part of the venn diagram has more
overlap with memes like complexity
theory and this is just my sense i don't
know it very well
and things like permaculture and i see
the word regeneration thrown around a
lot which is which i take to be like a
specific
um part of the overall like green green
movement or green technology movement
um but they seem to be
talking about like red pills and gray
pills they seem to have been red pilled
away from that and now
further gray peeled away from that um
and then as for game b
it seems to have a lot of overlap
although not total overlap with
metamodernism
and from what i from what i understand
game b part part of why i like it is my
impression that it's actually quite
general
is that it's um it's describing game a
which is and correct me from wrong but
which i take to be a sort of
seeking of an omni-win scenario where
basically all
sentient beings can come into
some scenario where nobody feels like
they have to defect on one another or
lose
and just that attitude alone
distinguishes it from oh sorry
that would be game b um not not game a
so that the game b is the only win
scenario
and then game a is the more default
where you have these game theoretical
dynamics where there's tons of defection
going on
um and people aren't all sort of on the
same side so to speak and performing
sort of one global
optimization game in order to make all
all sentient beings either on earth or
beyond uh
have a good time that's that's my sense
and
um as for that the the overlap of that
with the
um the meta tribe it seems like that's
interestingly distinct from
the post-rationalist contingent at least
at least in terms of who's friends with
one another
and that maybe um blends more with uh
metamodernism
but that's just my outside view from not
being a part of the
the two scenes metamodernism and uh
yeah yeah and i actually wrote um
an article or a journal entry called
weird stoicism where i said like
you know the ones i vibe with most the
tribes are game b meta modernism post
rationality and integral theory um
and i and like there's two different
things you can look at you can look at
the tribal element like what is the vibe
of the tribe like what are the type of
people that get attracted to it
and then the propositions and i would
say the propositions are
like really compatible and just like
looking at different things like
metamodern is looking at
kind of a developmental lens you know
like there's pre-modernity there's
modernity there's post-majority and
there's meta modernity
where consists of these meta systematic
thinkers trying to make sense of like
you know or that
post-modern aftermath of all these
fragmented realities
uh and when i did that white paper that
had the multipolar war
i didn't know anything about made of
modernism but they all jumped on my
radar and they said oh we love this
article blah blah and that's how i
discovered them yeah so it's like a
meta-modern article but not knowing what
the term was
okay cool and where game b is sort of
like an instruction manual i find like a
really dry
instruction manual of like how game a
is problematic and then what game b
could be without having an understanding
of what it's going to look like
um so that's on a propositional level
and but they both
have the origins of um or they both were
influenced
by ken wilber and triple theory because
i know danish mochtenberger
he was influenced by ken wilbur um
hansey frynack
uh daniel gertz they were influenced by
wilbur they have criticism
of them obviously and then the post rat
they're probably in
um you know the same space but they came
from the rationalist
right uh kind of thing but then they
have a lot of overlap
propositionally by being like in a
meta-modern post-rational
space huh and i think kind of like estoa
and all these places are like
where they're kind of intersecting for
the first time right that's the thing i
was gonna say
to me as far as i can tell there are
four
maybe five hubs like formal hubs so
there's the stoa
where you see i i think the overlap of
all the demographic segments of the meta
tribe as far as i can tell the post rat
condition the ea contingent the meta
modernism game b
et cetera um silicon valley people
there's uh i haven't been to one yet but
the inter-intellect salons i think might
be another one of these
um another one seems to be
uh monastic academy where even just at
monastic academy like out of the monks
that are there full-time like wearing
their sashes and so on
there are there are people who came in
through less wrong
they're people and and who want to um
like fight
artificial intelligence risk like monks
who want to fight artificial
intelligence risk is
i just love that as a thing uh and then
there's
um there's one more i'm forgetting
um maybe it'll oh right
um the castle festival i don't know if
you've heard of that but it's what my uh
collaborator andre ornish runs um on a
yearly basis it didn't happen this year
because of coronavirus
but it had daniel schmuckenberger at it
and then it also had like ben todd from
80 000 hours
i'm not sure if will was there but i
know ben at least was and a bunch of
other ea folks
um and oh rep someone is saying in the
chat rebel wisdom
that might be another one too i've
really loved watching their videos oh
and uh actually there's a further one
which is i would say
uh evolving ground which is being
created right now by jared james
and charlie aubry um which is
interestingly like a bunch of
uh it's buddhism themed buddhist
vadriana
which is a very different type of
practice than traditional buddhism but
it seems to also bring together
like be a collecting basin for all the
different demographics
i'm curious if you've heard of any
others that are that are out there in
the woodwork
yeah i'd say you know there's rebel
wisdom future thinkers um
right uh justin murphy's indie thinkers
is kind of a little different the
kind of thread they're more reactionary
uh uh interesting i haven't heard of
that
but he has a community uh and i i should
have like did some uh
disclaimer like this is super insider
baseball
session that we have at the the stuff i
feel kind of bad
um but yeah let's let's take in some q a
so evan you had a question
yeah so um you described me to a t as a
many people in the chat were also
saying here um so thank you uh that
being said so
i've been struggling lately with
something which is that you know i've
really
pretty consciously and intentionally
stayed away from having any sort of uh
public-facing online presence since
pretty much literally the eternal
september
say like early 90s wow and it is pretty
early
i've been a fly on the wall for less
wrong and slight star codex and a bunch
of the other communities you mentioned
and i've engaged with
those communities a lot in person to
varying degrees
um and so that that was nice um
but it seems like to sort of join in
these sort of meta tribe conversations
as a full participant
these days that you have to have some
sort of fairly curated online presence
um you know you have to have a twitter
it helps if you have a blog or a podcast
so people know who the [ __ ] you
are right and uh and otherwise you know
there's a sense of like how does one
demonstrate one's qualifications to take
part in the higher level discussions
without those things so i'm curious
about your take on that you know that
level of what feels to me like sort of
self-promotion gives me some
like bad creepy vibes so you know how
how can one connect and contribute to
the discussion of the meta tribe without
being on twitter without having
a public-facing blog etc etc
well first of all epic background holy
crap um
but uh second of all i think part of why
i wanted to go into
talking about these different collect
collection points um
that peter and i just talked about is i
think a few of them basically anybody
can enter
so i think the stoa is one of these
where you're certainly
well the thing you're describing is real
like you're more likely to have heard
about the stella
if you have an online presence in the
first place um but also
a friend can just send you a link to the
stoa and you can pop into zoom
um i would say the same is maybe
i haven't investigated inter intellect
it might be similar in this way
um i would say evolving evolving ground
is also one of these more open things
where you can join the evolving ground
slack um i think their website is
evolvingground.org but i'm not sure
probably if you google it it'll pop up
oh awesome um but but to your point i
think you're pointing to a super
real thing and one one route around
this problem that i've seen people take
is there's a huge tradition now um
lasting a few few years maybe that's not
a tradition but there's there's um
there's a there's a new practice you
might say of making
what are called alts on twitter um where
people
uh who who similarly are not wanting to
be a part of public discussions under
their
under their actual names uh will sort of
build an online persona
or just their own version of themselves
and then have a
have an avatar that is maybe like a
photo of a roman statue
or some sort of crazy psychedelic art
or a historical portrait or or whatever
and
it will be named something other than
what they are like the famous one here i
think is uh eigenrobot
um who uh is i would say one of the
people at the center of this phenomenon
that i'm describing
and uh they they they tend to be
um able to play play the sort of game
that you're describing
without having to get personally
involved which comes with all sorts of
possible consequences like
having your old tweets dug up you know
in the future by some ai algorithm and
finding all the ways in which it's not
politically correct or something which
would not be ideal
um that said that you know creating an
alt still takes a
ton of effort um so it's not
you know it's not uh it's not like you
can just pop into that
um so beyond beyond the the the avenues
that i described of the other things
that anyone could just pop into peter
i'm curious if
um if you have thoughts about other ways
people could get involved if they're
similar to
uh for some reason your name isn't
popping up oh evan
if they're similar to evan where they've
been because because tons of most
i would say most of the people who i
would describe as meta tribe are
actually in evan's position
they say they say exactly the same
things like i've been around since
you know the early like extropians with
nick bostrom
or you know i've been around since the
beginning of less wrong like not only
less wrong 2.0 but less wrong 1.0 when
they reached slate star codex
but they they haven't found a good entry
point
right yeah and that's what i found um
with
i had a podcast before the store and i
called it intellectual explorers podcast
and i rebranded it to the store
and a lot of my podcast listeners came
to the stoa
because it's like oh i can participate
now because it's like an event
um and uh yeah two thousand come to mind
i just wanna
flag it like uh so at the hour we'll
stop recording but we'll have like a
free associated conversation i just
wanna have the recording so we can throw
this as
maybe a beacon for meta tribalists um
so the two thoughts came to mind with
the alt strategy
uh there's this uh i mentioned this
before but there's a satanic group
called the order of the nine angles it's
a memetic tribe
like titanic yeah and they're they're
just basically like they they um
recommend their
uh their people that uh the initiates to
sacrifice people they there's really
evil dark [ __ ] uh
we don't respect actual people yes to
get in okay and then one of their
um kind of initiate rights is to
uh they call it the insight roles is to
join extremist organization whether it's
like an islamic terrorist group
or um like some kind of uh white
nationalist group
and embody it completely in order to
dismantle uh you know the the
civilization's western civilization's
grasp on them just that
your subjective prison and so they just
radically free themselves and then they
can pursue the the satanic goal whatever
it is
so but like maybe repurposing
fascinating for good though
like that's the kind of old strategy
where you can kind of create an all join
like maybe a social justice twitter or
join a post right twitter or whatever
um that's cool and you can authentically
be an old like you just like hey this is
just my alt account
um and then just really embody that
tribe
to kind of like feel it fight with it
learn from it beautiful
and then maybe shake it off um so yeah
that came from i think that's a pretty
cool strategy
uh and then the other thing to answer
evan's question is um
i think this raul has something called
netplay in comparison to like networking
uh so basically your network increases
by just playing and that's how i treated
my podcast it's like i had a podcast
oh my god people are so willing to come
on podcast i didn't like i had no show
notes i didn't do anything i just wanted
to talk to cool people
and then just like like i rekindled my
friendship with i wasn't friends with
him at times but he was a
student uh teacher relationship with
john varvakey and then we became
like a research project together so
maybe using repurposing these game a
tools like podcasting or whatever
as a way to net play in order to find
the others
and actually on that note um my you know
i wasn't
i wasn't really on twitter until maybe a
year ago when when all these people like
michael kersey and samo buryar were
telling me you gotta get on twitter it's
like where the action is happening
and i kept starting and stopping because
i was under
something like 500 followers and it just
didn't feel like a conversation
and then the thing that ended up working
for me because there is a pretty high
startup cost on something like twitter
which is basically treating it as a as
an intellectual sketchpad
where i just worked out my ideas in
public and then eventually
like people i slowly got follows and now
it's to the point where there are enough
followers where i can actually have
actual conversations with people like
people who regularly chime in
i think there are probably even a few
people here who i do that with who i
found through those means
um but i think if i uh if i just
started on twitter and was like huh how
come nobody's engaging
anything that i say then i probably
would have given up in like the first i
mean i did give up like a few times
and then i was just like well okay i can
just treat this is basically evernote
but live like live in public
and an alt would probably even help more
with that because you're less afraid of
you're less that you're less attached to
your thoughts right if someone takes a
crap
on your beautiful idea then at least
they're not taking a crap on you
uh this let's go to a pivot to a
question steph you had a question
are you here in the room still okay yeah
i can i can
just sort of read it um
yeah so i don't know i was i was
wondering more about sort of like the
social
slash emotional um impact
of uh i guess being a meta triber
um you know tyler you mentioned
um sort of having to play a different
game with every group
um do you sort of feel
i don't know do you think it's possible
to sort of have
um true meaningful friendships quote
unquote
with uh people who identify with a more
traditional tribe say um
and what do you sort of do when they
um if you come into a situation where
they're like smearing or slandering like
people in other tribes people who you
care about
and you sort of know that that's like
not a fair depiction of them
right yeah yeah well
so to answer the first part um
i mean like like i said i think it
becomes um as
as you go from like blue pill to red
pill to gray pill it becomes more and
more challenging to
um to to feel connection with people
with a
more traditional orientation to begin
with at least
and then over time i've found
that it's become easier and easier
and why is that um
i mean for me actually i don't know if
this is a this is a
prescription for everyone but for me
something that's helped
is just going deeper into my uh
meditation practice and also in
particular practicing meta
um where you know i sort of don't
associate people with their particular
ideas um
i don't see that as being representative
of them per se
um the way the way i interact with
people when i move through the world
is that sort of everyone is both this
sort of a
god beast and a baby at the same time um
and those are all things worthy of uh
to borrow from c.s lewis worthy of
worship um
and if you i find that if i just focus
on those those
core parts that are worthy of worship
they can say whatever they want and it
doesn't matter i feel i feel a really
deep connection with them
um but then you i think you still need
to interact with that second layer that
you mentioned
um because they're often you know going
to be directly insulting your friends
um you know like someone who i
spend time with nearly every day um
was talking about trump supporters the
other day and
talking about them as if they didn't
deserve to live like that's pretty
intense
um so in those cases i actually find
those as
i forget i think it was either peter or
peter quoting jason
talking about the opportunity for shadow
work in these areas
um i find that there's both
opportunities to do that sort of shadow
work in these areas like find
why am i triggered by them talking about
this in this way to explore one's own
value set
but then furthermore i think it's just
really important to understand
how ideas interact with people in
general especially in these really
profound ways where they start to
identify
their souls almost with the ideas um so
i usually treat these as opportunities
to just ask them questions about their
perspective
and note along the way where i get
triggered which is useful information
but
you know if i for instance if i meet
someone who's like um
all trump supporters should die or like
all billionaires should die
i i my reaction now is i try to get
actually pretty interested in that i
don't have to believe that to be
interested in it
i can be like huh so when you mean died
you mean like literally like
they should they should be killed and
maybe they say yes i'm like okay but how
like
should we send them to like should we
guillotine them
and they're like well no i'm like well
should we uh
i don't know firing squads and they're
like okay no not really that and like so
by die maybe you don't mean literally
kill them you just mean that they're bad
and and it kind of helps me understand
um how the how the dialect and the ideas
interact with
their actual behavioral stances and
preferences which to me is just a
fascinating opportunity for
um understanding how human nature works
um and how human nature interacts with
culture
so i i sort of do this duel thing where
it's like
um in terms of where the connection is i
feel the connection on the level
of the god the baby and the beast um but
then
that's but then but then on top of that
you can you can do this meta game as
peter might describe it of
trying to understand like how do these
ideas operate in a human mind
um and maybe maybe there are things
about them that i missed
um like i would be pretty surprised if
it turns out that
i should come to believe that trump
supporters and billionaires should die
but maybe there are aspects of trump
supporters or billionaires that are
harmful for human flourishing
that i had that i don't know about yet
and maybe i should try to understand
those because
certainly they're going to be other
examples in the world of that sort of
particular instance um does that help
stephanie
yeah that's really helpful actually
thanks i'd be curious how it goes if
you're uh
if you if you try practicing it um are
you the person on twitter who
originally posted that thing okay yeah
plea please let me know if um
if that helps
all right um um
[Music]
um you had a question that tags on
kevin's question do you want to maybe
address something kevin said and then uh
state your question yeah i i just copied
and pasted his
text really he had a two-part question
about basically as a communication
revolution increases
uh only 60 of the world online now as
more and
more people get online that part two was
which parts of kind of theory and
techniques and tools
for synthesizing world views would be
useful
so is the question um let me see if i
can restate it and if i understand it is
it something like
um right now not everyone is online but
in the future
a ton more people in perspective thus
perspectives and techniques and so on
will be online
how how would um something like the meta
tribe go about
understanding um how to prioritize
between these things as being useful or
is it um
yeah i think that it ends kind of is
there really
tools or techniques that would kind of
help these new parts to
be useful for these new participants in
the global
meaning making machine so
tips yeah i could say a lot of things
let me think for a moment uh peter do
you have anything that comes to mind
not at the moment i think yeah i think
the
for some reason you know they're like i
said there there's so many things that
one could say here
but two things come most immediately to
mind and i don't know if that's because
they're the best ones or
because they're just top of mind for
whatever reason i think both of them i
was talking about today so that's
probably the actual reason which is
um one is um i got this from julia
gayliff actually
um julia gailiff is a podcaster in the
rationality movement
i think i think that's a fair
description and she has an amazing
podcast what is it called uh rationally
speaking
um which is actually one of my entry
points before i even knew about
effective altruism or the rationality
movement i was listening to julia
gailiff
um and then um she
she had this practice that i that i
started adopting which is just noticing
your own confusion
um which sounds so simple and it's like
okay but that sounds really basic how is
that even a technique but it turns out
it's not
like if if you start no if you start
really rigorously going throughout the
day noticing your
your own confusion you'll start noticing
that like
most of the day you're actually confused
at least some part of you is
um and you'll start noticing also this
counter force
to squash the confusion or pretend it's
not there
um so i think this is going to be one of
the best
uh practices for the situation you
describe where now you're having this
this greater and greater collision of
more of a more globalized world where
all these ideas are
circulating and intermeshing and
opposing one another
the temptation of a human mind that
seeks coherence
can often just be try to come up with
here's what's really going on which is
sort of a one-size-fits-all
ideology that kind of explains away
everything else and that eventually just
minimizes
confusion but at the cost
of constantly suppressing thoughts to
the contrary
um so i think basically what noticing or
confusion helps you do
is sort of institute a philosophy
similar to the philosopher of science
thomas kuhn where it's it's fine i think
to take a
his idea was that it's fine to take a
provisional theory
okay wasn't this prescriptive but this
is this is the version that i'll say
that it's fine to take a provisional
theory about what's really going on
or what's going on um and oh someone
wrote make confusion sexy yeah i i agree
ryan
that's so awesome um but then but then
along with this
with this explanatory framework which
you kind of need to operate through the
world
otherwise you become that sort of
postmodernist xbox xbox player who's
just like screw everything
nothing is meaningful i'm just gonna you
know
chill all day or or pursue hedonism the
thing you need to do
is maintain some purpose
or or overall explanatory framework or
both but then at the same time
um not get seduced by it and as
feynman said richard time in the famous
physicist the easiest person to trick is
yourself so
noticing confusion can help you exit the
delusion
of um these idea storms sort of taking
taking hold of you and not letting you
go um
and the way
the way i've started doing this because
i realized at a certain point but i'm
actually not
as good at this as i would like is just
whenever i notice something that is
um anomalous um to my mainstream
perspective
i'll even just say out loud i tweeted
about this today i'll just say out loud
anomaly which obviously makes me seem
you know
incredibly sane um but uh it's been
helping a lot like even with little
things like the other day i wrote about
this too i was
i drove to the grocery store and when i
parked i heard like a little
soft thump on the side of my seat and i
i looked down and
there was nothing there and so i was
like oh that's weird and i walked out of
my car
until i realized oh and i said anomaly i
said it out loud but i didn't invest
enough
curiosity in my own confusion there that
there was just a random thump sound in
my car
and then as soon as i walked down my car
i realized and i was about to shut the
door
and i realized i left my keys in there
and i was about to lock myself
out and so
i looked under the seat and like lo and
behold upon a second glance there
went where there were my keys but pretty
much every time i've
said anomaly out loud and not
investigated i've regretted it it's
always been something like really
important like that
and all the more important for these um
all-pervading
ideologies or world views that direct
almost all of our actions
so if you don't notice anomalies with
those and and try to collapse your
kuni and paradigm or your your guiding
theory or guiding explanation or
worldview
the more you're going to be sucked into
a matrix of your own creation
so um i said i was going to say two but
i'm already monologued on one so let's
just
go with noticing your own confusion and
like ryan said making it sexy which is
even better
you know on that point um and we'll
close out after after this and maybe
have a free associative conversation
as being a facilitator i always check in
with my body um
and then kind of check in with the field
and there's there's like kind of a
ickiness uh going on in this session for
me it's nothing to do with you
uh tyler but it felt like a masturbatory
kind of thing like we're talking about
this thing it's so abstract and i'm like
oh people are enjoying themselves and
was
what's boring with this inside baseball
thing just felt kind of like a little
bit
yucky that made me think though it's
like
there's no other memetic tribe that does
this that just has like even considers
himself a tribe really
and then has this kind of like hyper
like um
analysis self-analysis on themselves
right um so that's the tribe that goes
oh no are we being too tribal right now
yeah yeah and then by doing this makes
that gives that icy feeling makes me not
want to be a part of like you know a
meta tribe or whatever
um and and it's like you know when
everyone first starts masturbating they
feel guilty or yucky so maybe this is a
phase that
we have to have to go through together
um
in order to have like you know sex but
uh this
this thing with or becoming body away
from a medic trap to come and body tribe
um yeah and uh yeah with with the other
magnetic tribes it's just like there's
an ecology that they're in
uh that they're just supporting
themselves with jokey memes or whatever
and then they're just warring outside of
it so they're just really kind of like
trying to fight for a map of reality
really and then not really kind of
questioning it
uh but whatever this meta tribe is
is um doing that i i think
well you know it's funny to use the word
masturbation because
okay please don't tweet what i'm about
to say but it the thought came to mind
um something like a lot of the most
world-changing things are founded
upon some initial like group
masturbation which is basically you you
have to set the ground
of what is this thing what are we all
talking about what do we share in common
um
before actually turning your attention
toward doing stuff in the world
and so the pretty much the only reason i
give a crap about
um the metatrade being a thing um as as
a thing that exists in the world
i mean well for one it's just it's a
good way to make friends
um who i get along with but on the other
you know my background is in effective
altruism and i still adhere
not necessarily to the mainstream effect
of altruism philosophy but at least to
the idea
that my entire life is in service of all
sentient beings
and so uh my interest is
sort of setting a ground um
creating fertile ground for the people
who are willing
and able to take that task on and that's
a pretty difficult
um gardening task um because i think
there are lots of iterations where even
if they're just a little bit off like
oops you ended up with communist russia
and now like
tons of people are getting sent to the
gulags in the name of um
in the name of something that was
originally like a beautiful ideal
i would rather not replicate that but in
order to not replicate those sorts of
things
there does need to be this initial thing
which might kind of feel like oh how
many angels are dancing on the head of
the pen
um which is basically this sort of like
the
the sort of masturbatory feeling thing
which is just defining like what are we
what are we about
um who are our people um what is not
this thing what is this thing
and that can feel like just playing
insider baseball but i think that's
that's in my mind that's kind of a
necessary process but ideally it would
be done in tandem with
um something in more outward staring um
so i agree with you there
yeah and it's not just uh like here at
the store we have all sorts of practices
that we're doing that are dealing with
trauma
you know dealing with the meta system
thinking so i think it's like a
combination all that stuff is needed
and it's like socrates you know it's
like um he knows he knows nothing
and then the best life is the you know
the examine life
and i think that's kind of what we need
to do here in the liminal so
that being said i'm going to stop um the
recording and i'm going to go to the
washroom uh
so if anyone has to leave right now you
can take a bio break and then
maybe we'll just start up a free
associative conversation whoever wants
to stay
sounds cool all right let's play some
music and